# Lukas José Ferrer

https://github.com/Ljferrer lukasjferrer@gmail.com || 310.801.8751

# **ABOUT ME**

I studied Bio, EE, and AI to see neurons from all three perspectives. My initial work on electrophysiology, medical devices, and VR gave me experience bringing research into reality. As a self taught programmer, I now focus on Deep Learning and NLP applied towards Information Retrieval Systems.

# **EDUCATION**

## M.S. BIOMEDICAL ENG.

USC | VITERBI

August 2017 | Los Angeles, CA Focus: Electrophysiology, Medical Signal Processing, & Agile Software Development

## **B.S. BIOMEDICAL ENG.**

USC | Viterbi

May 2016 | Los Angeles, CA Focus: Medical Devices & Physiological Modeling

# TOOLS

## **PYTHON**

PyTorch | FastAI TensorFlow | Keras TensorBoard Numpy SpaCy Faiss REST | Requests

### **SOFTWARE**

Linux | Ubuntu | CentOS Amazon Web Services Docker MATLAB LabVIEW SolidWorks

# LINKS

LinkedIn || Iukas-ferrer Live Demo || ResearchTool Backend || DIG-Text-Similarity-Search GitHub || Ljferrer

## **EXPERIENCE**

## **INFORMATION SCIENCES INSTITUTE** | RESEARCH PROGRAMMER

May 2018 - Present | Marina del Rey, CA

- SARAL Working with Transformers for low resource machine translation
- Reimplemented several academic papers in PyTorch
- Improved our existing NMT system's performance by 1.5 BLEU by incorporating Stochastic Depth to train a 50% deeper model
- Operationalized our models to fit into the larger SARAL pipeline i.e. Audio/Text Database -> ASR -> NMT -> IR -> Summarization -> User
- **SAGE** Implemented the backend of SAGE's in-house **Research Tool**, a news database that uses sentence embeddings made with TensorFlow, finds nearest neighboring hits with Faiss, and is deployed as a Restful API
- Set up a host server on AWS and automated the ingestion pipeline that continuously updates the Research Tool with +100,000 news articles per day from LexisNexis

# KECK RADIOMICS LAB | VOLUNTEER RESEARCHER

Oct 2016 - Nov 2017 | Los Angeles, CA

- Analyzed spectral and texture features of CT images with a particular focus on boundary conditions for tissue segmentation in a HIPAA compliant setting
- Characterized the statistical variance of images across different CT machines

# BRAIN-MONITORING DEFIBRILLATOR | FINAL PROJECT

Sept 2016 - Dec 2016 | USC BME 620

- Proposed the design of an implantable Class III medical device that monitors brain activity to accurately determine when a patient with extreme cardiovascular risk is in need of defibrillation
- Identified a less invasive alternative to increase the patient's quality of life and charted *this* hypothetical path to market through the FDA instead

## **RECALL VR** | CREATOR AND TEAM LEAD

Aug 2015 - May 2016 | USC GamePipe Lab

- Envisioned and pursued the creation of an experimental, Virtual Reality learning accelerator designed to leverage a student's natural spatial awareness to increase memory retention (sometimes called The Memory Palace Technique)
- Led 16+ students with skill sets ranging from architecture and animation to computer science and business under an Agile development framework
- Won 1st place at the 2016 Viterbi Senior Design Expo
- Declined several investment opportunities to create a VR Education startup
- Ultimately, the experience drove me to teach myself Machine Learning & Al

## **HEMODIALYSIS CATHETER** | FINAL PROJECT

May 2015 - Aug 2015 | USC MPTX 513

• Designed a novel Class II implantable medical device for a faux-510(k) to simulate the process of obtaining FDA clearance to market

#### **SYNTOUCH** | ROBOTICS INTERN

Feb 2014 - Nov 2014 | Los Angeles, CA

- Fabricated a robotic test fixture to explore alternative applications of SynTouch's new tactile sensor, the NumaTac
- Reported weekly progress at the Medical Device Development & Fabrication Lab at USC under the direction of Dr. Gerald E. Loeb